hey what's going on guys welcome to a
new series now for those of you waiting
on laravel the premium course the crash
course and the youtube project should
all be released within the next few
weeks so in this series what we're going
to be doing is creating a nodejs and
express application from absolute
scratch so the idea of this series is to
be very very beginner friendly and to be
kind of a continuation off of my node.js
for beginners crash course alright so
after people finish that this gives them
the opportunity to actually create a
project with node and express in a bunch
of other technologies ok so this will be
from absolute scratch we're going to
start on a machine that doesn't even
have no js' or Express or MongoDB
installed we're going to go through the
installations we're going to set up the
environment and then there's going to be
no generators no copying and pasting the
goal of this is to write and explain
every line of code so that you guys can
really grasp what's going on as opposed
to just watching a demo of an app being
built alright so if you have a little
experience with node and express in
MongoDB that's great if you don't even
know what those are I would suggest
watching these three videos here they're
there on my channel I was just watching
those before tempting the course or the
series alright now as far as the
application goes it's going to be very
simple in terms of functionality at
least at first we're going to be able to
create read update and delete articles
stored in a MongoDB database from our
node and Express app all right so let's
take a look at some of the technologies
that we'll be using and learning so
nodejs and npm nodejs is a JavaScript
runtime and server-side technology and
it comes with NPM which is node package
manager and this is used to install
modules like Express and thousands of
others okay so Express is a back-end
framework for building powerful
applications web applications
MongoDB which is a no SQL database
mongoose which is an ORM or an object
relational mapper and this allows our
application to interface with MongoDB
we'll be using the pug template engine
for our views pug is formally known as J
we'll be installing bootstrap a few
videos in and we're going to use Bower
for that which is a front-end package
manager similar to NPM we'll also do a
little bit of jQuery and Ajax to make
delete requests to our server alright so
I try not to mention this stuff too much
but I do have a patreon if you guys want
to support this channel directly even
$1.00 per month is greatly appreciated
if there's enough people that can help
out then I'll be able to do this stuff
full-time which is my goal and I'm also
working on some exclusive content and
perks for patrons for one-time donations
I have a paypal dot me account and then
if you're interested in premium courses
I have affiliate links at traversée
Mediacom slash edge' wanax courses
alright and I will be creating my own
courses very very soon so that's it guys
let's go ahead and get started on this
project and hopefully you enjoy it
alright guys in this video we're going
to be setting up our environment so
we're going to install a couple things
to build our application now I'm using
Windows because I want this to be
completely beginner friendly and I know
that a lot of people that are just
getting into web development and so on
maybe on Windows alright
but this is completely cross-platform
all the code we write everything it
doesn't matter what system you're on
alright so we're going to install a
couple things of course we need nodejs
and nodejs is a JavaScript runtime if
you have no clue what nodejs is I would
suggest watching my node for beginners
video we're going to install that that
also comes with NPM which is node
package manager and that's a command
line tool that we can use to install
different modules like Express and
Mongoose and so on
alright we're also going to need a
database and we're going to use MongoDB
long would you be is a no SQL database
if you want to learn more about Mongo
I'd suggest my MongoDB in 30 minutes
video I also just did a video called a
guide to know SQL databases if you want
to learn more about no SQL in general
we're also going to be using atom which
is a text editor this is what I've been
using for the most part lately and it's
it's a really nice editor it's by github
it's very very
well as far as looks and themes and it
also has a bunch of packages that you
can install that will help you with
development so we're going to install
that and then sensitive on Windows we
need a better command line because the
the standard CMD command line in Windows
is garbage so we're going to be using
git bash okay so this right here get SCM
comm you can download it it's going to
download the git version control system
along with the command line tool called
git bash alright so let's get started
first thing we'll do is install nodejs
so we're going to just go ahead and
click here we're going to get the
recommended version which is at this
time six point ten point three and
that's going to just be an installer
we'll just go through it quickly
alright so let's open it up and just go
through this we'll click Next and it's
going to go into your Program Files if
you're on Windows click Next and install
alright and it's as easy as that nodejs
and NPM is now installed so next thing
we're going to do is we're going to
install MongoDB so let's go ahead and go
to C download and there's a few steps
that we need to do here some of which
are in the command line but it's not too
bad so we're going to grab the yeah
windows 64-bit 2008 and later and that's
going to download the MSI file so this
is another installer that we need to go
through and it is a hundred and forty
eight megabytes so it may take a couple
minutes to download so once it's
downloaded just open it up and we're
going to go through this next and I'm
going to click custom right here because
I want to change the install path by
default it's going to be Program Files
MongoDB server and then the version I
don't want that I want it to be right in
the C Drive
so let's go to local C Drive and what
I'll do here is create a new folder
called MongoDB alright and that's where
we want this to be installed c / MongoDB
will click Next and then install and
it's going to go through the setup okay
so we'll click finish now there's a
couple extra steps we need to take we
need to go into that folder that we just
installed it in so for me it's going to
be C Drive MongoDB and we're going to
create a folder here called data alright
and then inside the data folder we're
going to create another folder called DB
this is where all of our data will be
stored now we have to also create a
log-log folder so it's a new folder log
alright and then we need to open up a
command line and I haven't installed git
bash yet so we'll just use the standard
command prompt so it's a CMD and we'll
run that as administrator okay and then
let's see so I'm going to navigate to
that folder so we want to go to CD
MongoDB and we actually want to go in
the bin folder alright if we look at
what's in there oops can't do that
there is a vis MongoDB XE that's the
main program so we need to run that with
some options or some flags so let's say
Mongo D and then we're going to do - -
let me make this a little bigger so you
guys can see it see I haven't done this
in a while
font let's make it 28 there we go
alright so Mongo D directory oops why
isn't that typing directory and it's
going to be per DB okay directory / DB
and then - - DB path
and then we want to define that data
path that we created so it's going to be
in your MongoDB MongoDB folder slash
data slash the B okay that's the folder
we just created so what we're doing is
we're specifying the database path as
that folder all right or that location
then we need to specify the log path
okay so that is going to be C slash
MongoDB slash log and it's going to be a
file called Hmong Mongo dot log and
it'll create that on its own then we
just want to add a couple more flags
here - - log append
we also want to do dash dash rest and
dash dash install ok and then that will
install it as a service so that it runs
in the background we don't have to
manually start and stop at all the time
and so on
so let's go ahead and click enter and
next thing we want to do is start the
MongoDB service so to do that we can say
net start MongoDB okay now it says the
services started successfully so that's
it MongoDB is now installed it's running
and we can now interact with it from
from our application so let's go ahead
and close that up and then we're going
to move on we're going to install Adam
which is the text editor so I'm just
going to click download all right so
once that's done we're just going to
open that up and the Adam installer is
is really weird because it does
everything behind the scenes you'll see
this little splash screen and then once
it's done it'll just be installed on
your system alright Adam is it Adam was
actually created with JavaScript it uses
electron which is a JavaScript framework
that allows you to build desktop
applications with JavaScript which is
really cool and I do have an intro to
electron video if you're interested in
that
all right so it's installed Adam and
started it up I'm just going to get rid
of this stuff this is just because I had
it installed previously so let me just
remove that project and then this is
just kind of a welcome screen if you
want to open a project install packages
and so on but we're going to close all
that up and will most likely install
some packages but we're going to do that
later on all right so we can close that
for now and then we're going to move on
to install git and get bash so let's
click this download for Windows if
you're using a Mac you can go to
download slash Mac and get this same
same program all right so that's going
to start it's only 35 megabytes so it
shouldn't take too long to download all
right so we'll open that up and we're
just going to go through this it's going
to install it in your Program Files and
then for this we'll just leave all the
defaults and then when you see this
option I always choose this because this
will add optional UNIX tools to the
regular Windows command prompt so for
instance LS you saw that I tried doing
that in the regular command line and it
didn't work so it'll add that it'll add
a whole bunch of stuff so I always
choose that and then for the rest of
this stuff we're going to leave the
default open SSL library that's good
windows style click Next Next and enable
filesystem caching we'll leave that
credential manager we'll leave that and
we'll click install all right so that's
all set now
let's go ahead and click launch git bash
and then this is the command-line tool
so we can make this bigger with can
holding ctrl and then scroll the mouse
wheel and just to check to make sure
that node is installed we can say node
dash B you can see we have version six
point seven point three and we can also
say NP
- B and we have version three point
seven point ten so that's it for setting
setting up our environment in the next
video we're going to start - to build
out our application will create our
package JSON file and we'll go from
there